<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Candide, ou l'Optimisme: Chapter 1</title>
        <title type="sub">A TEI P5 Digital Edition</title>
        <author>
          <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/36925746">
            Voltaire
          </persName>
        </author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <name ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3788-7210">
            Sridipa Dandapat
          </name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Sridipa Dandapat</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Independent Digital Edition</pubPlace>
        <date when="2026">2026</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            This TEI encoding is licensed under a Creative Commons
            Attribution 4.0 International Licence.
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Voltaire</author>
          <title>Candide</title>
          <editor>Unknown</editor>
          <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
          <date when="1759">Originally published 1759</date>
          <ptr target="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/19942/19942-h/19942-h.htm"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects">
          <term>Philosophical fiction</term>
          <term>Satire, French</term>
          <term>Enlightenment literature</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026" who="#SD">Initial TEI P5 encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
        <head>Chapter 1</head>
        <head type="sub">How Candide was brought up in a magnificent castle,
        and how he was expelled thence</head>

        <p>In a castle of <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2921044">
        Westphalia</placeName>, lived a youth whom nature had endowed with
        the most agreeable manners. His face was the index of his mind.
        He had a solid judgment joined to the most unaffected simplicity;
        and hence, I presume, he had his name of
        <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName>.</p>

        <p>The old servants of the family suspected him to have been the son
        of <persName type="fictional">the Baron</persName>'s sister, by a
        good, honest gentleman of the neighborhood, whom that young lady
        refused to marry, because he could only produce threescore and
        eleven quarterings in his arms; the rest of the genealogical tree
        belonging to the family having been lost through the injuries of time.</p>

        <p>The <persName type="fictional">Baron</persName> was one of the most
        powerful lords in <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2921044">
        Westphalia</placeName>, for his castle had a gate and several windows,
        and his great hall was even hung with tapestry.</p>

        <p>The <persName type="fictional">Baroness</persName>, who weighed
        three hundred and fifty pounds, consequently was a person of great
        consideration, and she did the honours of the house with a dignity
        that commanded universal respect.</p>

        <p>Her daughter <persName type="fictional">Cunégonde</persName> was
        seventeen years of age, fresh-coloured, comely, plump, and
        desirable.</p>

        <p>The Baron's son appeared in every respect worthy of his father.
        The Preceptor <persName type="fictional">Pangloss</persName> was the
        oracle of the family, and little
        <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName> listened to his
        instructions with all the good faith of his age and
        character.</p>

        <p><persName type="fictional">Pangloss</persName> taught
        metaphysico-theologo-cosmolo-nigology. He could prove to admiration
        that there is no effect without a cause; and, that in this best of
        all possible worlds, the
        <persName type="fictional">Baron</persName>'s castle was the most
        magnificent of all castles, and My Lady the best of all possible
        baronesses.</p>

        <p>It is demonstrable, said he, that things cannot be otherwise than
        as they are; for as all things have been created for some end, they
        must necessarily be created for the best end. Observe, for instance,
        the nose is formed for spectacles, therefore we wear spectacles.</p>

        <p><persName type="fictional">Candide</persName>, convinced of this
        doctrine, believed that
        <persName type="fictional">Cunégonde</persName> was a great beauty,
        though he had never had the boldness to tell her so. He concluded
        that after the happiness of being born of
        <persName type="fictional">Baron Thunder-ten-tronckh</persName>,
        the second degree of happiness was to be
        <persName type="fictional">Miss Cunégonde</persName>, the third that
        of seeing her every day, and the fourth that of hearing
        <persName type="fictional">Doctor Pangloss</persName>, the greatest
        philosopher of the whole province, and consequently of the whole
        world.</p>

        <p>One day <persName type="fictional">Cunégonde</persName>, while
        walking near the castle, in a little wood which they called a park,
        saw between the bushes, Dr.
        <persName type="fictional">Pangloss</persName> giving a lesson in
        experimental natural philosophy to her mother's chamber-maid, a
        little brown wench, very pretty and very docile.</p>

        <p>As <persName type="fictional">Miss Cunégonde</persName> had a
        great disposition for the sciences, she breathlessly observed the
        repeated experiments of which she was a witness; she clearly
        perceived the force of the Doctor's reasons, the effects, and the
        causes; she turned back greatly flurried, quite pensive, and filled
        with the desire of knowledge, imagining that she might be a
        sufficiently reason for young
        <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName>, and he for her.</p>

        <p>She met <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName> on reaching
        the castle and blushed; he blushed also; she wished him good morning
        with a faltering voice, and he wished her good morning with equal
        embarrassment. The next day, after dinner, as they were rising from
        table, <persName type="fictional">Cunégonde</persName> and
        <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName> found themselves
        behind a screen;
        <persName type="fictional">Cunégonde</persName> let fall her
        handkerchief, <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName> picked
        it up, she innocently took hold of his hand, and he as innocently
        kissed hers with a warmth, a sensibility, a grace — all very
        particular; their lips met, their eyes sparkled, their knees
        trembled, their hands strayed.</p>

        <p>The <persName type="fictional">Baron Thunder-ten-tronckh</persName>
        passed near the screen and beholding this cause and effect, expelled
        <persName type="fictional">Candide</persName> from the castle with
        great kicks. <persName type="fictional">Cunégonde</persName> fainted
        away, and as soon as she came to herself, the
        <persName type="fictional">Baroness</persName> boxed her ears. Thus
        a general consternation was spread over this most magnificent and
        most agreeable of all possible castles.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
